<document>
	<properties>
		<author>Sérgio Taborda</author>
		<title>Managed File</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
	<section name="Managed File Toolbox">
		<p>
			I/O operations are many times considered boundary, less important, operations, however they are most frequently used, in an almost omnipresent awy in all applications
			and in more that one flavor. Web applications, for example, often must cope with file download/upload features that are 
			copied to a local filesystem. Commonly these features are introduced with the support of a third party API, 
			and the real work boils down to stream plumbing.
		</p>
		<p>
			Java allows for OS file system manipulation as we see fit in a very paltaform independent way, specilly by means of <code>java.io.File</code> class. 
			However Jar/Zip files that also may contain files and file groups like their where folders have a very different treatment.
			If you think of jar/zip file like a kind of <i>virtual file</i>, java does not support this idea directly. 
			This idea is not new of far-fetched ( e.g. Windows XP and beyond already supports zip files under this this virtual file concept ).
		</p>
		<p>
			The Managed File Toolbox allows for total abstraction of the underlying file system and allows for the creation of complex virtual filesystem 
			based upon any other file-similar or file handling technology like FTP, HTTP, Zip and of course the OS native file system.
		</p>
	</section>
	<section name="File vs Managed File" >
		<p>
			A Managed File is a node in the file system similarly to <code>java.io.File</code>.
			The main difference is on how to obtain an <code>InputStream</code> or <code>OutputStream</code> from the file.
			Java IO uses the Adapter Pattern approach to create streams. MiddleHeaven's Managed File uses a simples Factory Method
			that will return a <code>ManagedFileContent</code>
		</p>
		<p>
			A Managed File can be copied to another file or folder simply by invoking <code>copyTo</code>. This can be a boring task
			in standard Java has no copy utility is provided and we end writing it over and over. 
		</p>
		<p>
			The root repositories for files and folders can be obtained by abstracting any supported URI or <code>java.io.File</code>.
			This task in normally done in bootstrap code. We will come back to this when we visit the Bootstrap and Service toolboxes 
			
		</p>
	</section>
	<section name="Model" >
		<p>
			The figure below illustrates the basic types for the Managed File Toolbox in MiddleHeaven.
			<figure>
			<img src="managedfileuml.png" />
			</figure>
			The <code>ManagedFile</code> is obviously the main type. From it is possible to obtain other children files, or folders, and have access to
			<code>ManagedFileContent</code> with in turn provides <code>InputStream</code> and <code>OutputStream</code> to the file. 
		</p>	
		
	</section>
	<section name="Use">
		<p>
		Using a Managed File is very simple. In this example we create an empty file i nthe current folder, locate the JUnit.jar in a local 
		maven repository and copy it. 
		<source>
		//ManagedFileRepositories is an integration utilities class that allows 
		// for integration with java.io.File
			
		ManagedFile folder = ManagedFileRepositories.resolveFile(new File("."));

		assertTrue(folder.exists());
		
		// resolving is simply acquiring a location where the file should be.
		ManagedFile testJar = folder.resolveFile("test.jar");
		
		// if exists, delete it.
		if (testJar.exists()){
			testJar.delete();
		}
		
		// create a new (empty) file 
		testJar.createFile();
		
		// it must exist by now
		assertTrue(testJar.exists());
		
		// manually obtain the path to the repository
	    ManagedFile rep = ManagedFileRepositories.resolveFile(new File(System.getProperty("user.home") + "/.m2/repository/junit/junit/4.1"));
	    
	    // resolve the file 
	    ManagedFile junitJar = rep.resolveFile("junit-4.1.jar");
	    
	    // copy it to the location previous created
	    junitJar.copyTo(testJar);
	    
	    // this a jar file that contains other files. So listFiles() collection will not be empty
	    assertFalse(junitJar.listFiles().isEmpty());
	        
		</source> 
		</p>
		<p>
			This example shows how we can turn a java.io.File into a ManageRepository. 
			It also shows you who simple is to copy a file simply by invoking <code>copyTo</code>.
			Finally is present a simple example to ilustrate the complete abstraction of the virtual file system of a Zip file
			by iterating it as we would had done with any other Maanged File 
		</p>
	</section>
	<section name="Under the hood">
		<p>
			The had use the managed file concept in other applications an frameworks I've develop along the year.
			During this time I've crossed roads with Apache's Commons VFS that thrives on the same "virtual file" idea.
			Because MiddleHeaven main goal is to abstract implementations and third party libraries I could no use Commons VFS directly.
			Instead I came up with the <code>RepositoryEngine</code> concept. 
			A repository engine provides a root <code>ManagedFileResolver</code> in order to resolve the location of any file within.
		</p>
		<p>
			MiddleHeaven Managed File implementation is a almost direct translation of Common VFS witch already provides a vast 
			variety of virtual systems like FTP and ZIP file , to name a few. Plans exist to incorporate WebDav and others.
		</p>
		<p>
			However Commons VFS does not integrate natively with Commons Upload commonly use in web applications to mediate file upload logic.
			This is where MiddleHeaven Managed File Toolbox architecture shines enabling the toolbox to provide the services we need based 
			upon on the code we see most useful. MiddleHeaven Managed File Toolbox provides a Managed File implementation of a ManagedRepository 
			that can be used to interact with the download files in the same exact way we would interact with a file on the disk.
			We'll talk more about this we we visit the Web Toolbox. 
		</p>
	</section>
	</body>
</document>